Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans Records 1836-1972 MS 24
New-York Historical Society
Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans records
1836-1972 (bulk 1850-1936)
New-York Historical Society
Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans (New York, N.Y.)
MS 24
6 Linear feet (40 volumes, 1 box)
The records of the Colored Orphan Asylum document the activities of the institution from 1836 to 1972, with the bulk of the records falling between 1850 and 1936. The records include minutes of general meetings, the Executive Committee, the Indenturing Committee and the After-Care Committee; volumes recording indentures; administrative correspondence; financial records; admission and discharge reports; newspaper clippings; reminiscences; visitor registers; and building plans. These records document the internal workings of an institution dedicated to educating and training African-American orphans in New York City. The Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans Records, with the exception of restricted material and Series IX, are digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in thirteen chronological series:
Series I: Minutes of Board Meetings
Series II. Minutes of the Executive Committee
Series III. Admission Records
Series IV. Indentures
Series V. Book of Records of Stipend Committee
Series VI. After-Care Committee Minutes
Series VII. Visitors Registers
Series VIII. Building Committee
Series IX. Bible
Series X. Centennial Booklet
Series XI. Miscellaneous Items
Series XII. Bequests
Series XIII. Property Material
Biographical / Historical
The Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans was founded in 1836 and was originally located on Fifth Avenue between 43rd and 44th Streets in Manhattan. In 1884, the institution was renamed the Colored Orphan Asylum and Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans; sometime after 1944, the name was again changed, this time to the Riverdale Children's Association. The institution was also relocated to Riverdale-on-Hudson.
The Asylum was among the earliest organizations in the country to provide housing, training, and employment specifically for African-American orphans. In the late 1880s, the Asylum adopted the "cottage-home" system, in which residents of varying ages lived in small groups under the supervision of a matron. The children in each cottage performed domestic chores. The system was thought to promote a less institutional atmosphere.
During the Draft Riots of July 14, 1863, the Colored Orphan Asylum was attacked by a mob, whose size was estimated by the New York Times at several hundred, mostly women and children. At that time, the Asylum housed some 600 to 800 homeless children in a large four story building surrounded by grounds and gardens. The crowd plundered the Asylum, even looting donated baby clothes, then set fire to the first floor despite the pleas of administrators. The building burned to the ground.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Colored Orphan Asylum document the activities of the institution from 1836 to 1972, with the bulk of the records falling between 1850 and 1936. The records include minutes of general meetings, the Executive Committee, the Indenturing Committee and the After-Care Committee; volumes recording indentures; administrative correspondence; financial records; admission and discharge reports; newspaper clippings; reminiscences; visitor registers; and building plans. These records document the internal workings of an institution dedicated to educating and training African-American orphans in New York City.
Correspondence.; Floor plans (orthographic projections); Guest registers; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; African American children -- Institutional care -- New York (State) -- New York.; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Children, Black -- Institutional care -- New York (State) -- New York.; Child labor -- New York (State) -- New York.; Draft Riot, New York, N.Y., 1863; Orphanages -- New York (State) -- New York.; Orphans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Riverdale Children's Association (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Minutes of Board Meetings, 1836-1965
  Scope and Contents
  Last 75 years restricted.
  Seventeen volumes. Volumes 1-14 are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1836 November 26 - 1840 December 18 (Volume 1)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1846 December - 1857 December 11 (Volume 2)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1863 July 25 - 1874 December 7 (Volume 3)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1874 December 14 - 1885 December 14 (Volume 4)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1886 January 8 - 1891 December 14 (Volume 5)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1892 January 8 - 1898 May (Volume 6)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1898 June 10 - 1903 January 2 (Volume 7)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1903 January 9 - 1908 January 10 (Volume 8)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1908 February 14 - 1910 December 12 (Volume 9)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1911 January 13 - 1914 May 8 (Volume 10)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1914 July 10 - 1921 December 12 (Volume 11)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1922 January - 1925 December (Volume 12)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1926 January - 1930 July (Volume 13)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1931 January - 1936 December (Volume 14)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1939 - 1945 (Volume 15)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1945 - 1953 (Volume 16)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1953 - 1965 (Volume 17)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1965 (Reel 1)
- Series II. Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1891-1938
  Five volumes. Unrestricted material is digitized are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1891 January - 1902 February (Volume 18)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1902 March 7 - 1913 November 7 (Volume 19)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1913 December 5 - 1917 April 5 (Volume 20)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1920 January - 1931 June 4 (Volume 21)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1931 November 6 - 1938 May 6 (Volume 22)
- Series III. Admission Records, 1837-1942
  Seven volumes. A number of volumes overlap in dates. Some contain short histories, indenture information, and discharges. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Admissions (with some indentures and short histories), 1837 - 1866 (Volume 23)
  - Admissions of Children (Volume 24)
  - Monthly Reports of Children Discharged and Received, 1859 - 1885 (Volume 25)
  - Admissions and Short Histories, 1867 - 1888 December (Volume 26)
  - Admissions, 1867 - 1912 (Volume 27)
  - Admissions and Discharges, 1885 - 1894 (Volume 28)
  - Admissions and Discharges, 1904 - 1942 (Volume 29)
- Series IV. Indentures, 1878-1916
  Six volumes. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Indentures, 1878 - 1898 (Volume 30)
  - Indentures, 1881 - 1910 (Volume 31)
  - Indentures, 1898 - 1911 (Volume 32)
  - Indentures--Accounting, 1860 - 1886 (Volume 33)
  - Indentures--Accounting, 1896 - 1929 (Volume 34)
  - Minutes of the Indenturing Committee, 1887 March - 1916 June (Volume 35)
- Series V. Book of Records of Stipend Committee, 1881-1905
  One volume. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Book of Records of Stipend Committee, 1881 - 1905 (Volume 36)
- Series VI. After-Care Committee Minutes, 1916-1933
  Two volumes. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - After-Care Committee Minutes, 1916 - 1923 (Volume 37)
  - After-Care Committee Minutes, 1923 - 1933 (Volume 38)
- Series VII. Visitors Registers, 1908-1947
  - Visitors Register, 1908 - 1935 (Volume 39)
  - Visitors Register, 1935 - 1947 (Volume 40)
- Series VIII. Building Committee, 1905-1907
  - Riverdale Property: Reports, Minutes, Correspondence, 1905 - 1907 (Volume 41)
- Series IX. Bible, undated
  One volume.
  - Bible used at Fifth Ave. and 43rd St. location. Rescued from the fire during the Draft Riots, July 1863., Undated (Volume 42)
- Series X. Centennial Booklet, 1936
  - "From Cherry Street to Green Pastures: A History of the Colored Orphan Asylum at Riverdale-on-Hudson, 1836-1936" (Volume 43)
- Series XI. Miscellaneous Items, 1853-1972
  Clippings, correspondence, minutes, ephemera. Fourteen items. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1853 - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1907 - 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series XII. Bequests, 1882-1893
  Six items. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Wills and bequests to the Association, [1883] - 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series XIII. Property Material, 1895-1961
  Last 75 years restricted. Unrestricted material is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Abstract of title of property at Amsterdam and 142nd St., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Approved building plans--12 E. 79th St., 1960 - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)